A Guide to the Rockefeller University records, President, Frederick Seitz, Campus, Series 4 FA817
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller University records, President, Frederick Seitz, Campus, Series 4
1968-1978
Rockefeller Archive Center
FA817
8 Cubic Feet 16 boxes
Biographical/Historical note
Frederick Seitz (b. July 4, 1911) is a physicist and science administrator. He has made fundamental contributions to the theory of solids, nuclear physics, fluorescence, and crystals, and has been a leader in the post - World War II scientific establishment in the United States. From 1968-1978 Seitz was president of the Rockefeller University.
Seitz entered Stanford University in January 1929, where he started out as a biochemistry major, but soon focused on mathematics and physics. He graduated from Stanford in three years with a degree in mathematics, and started doctoral studies in physics at Princeton University at the beginning of 1932. Completing his doctorate in 1934 Seitz remained at Princeton as a Proctor Fellow, and in 1935 was appointed as an instructor at the University of Rochester. In 1939 Seitz moved to the University of Pennsylvania first as assistant professor, 1939-1941, and then associate professor, 1941-1942, in the Morgan Laboratory of Physics. Seitz moved to the University of Illinois in 1949 to accept an appointment as a professor of Physics. In the 40s and 50s Seitz's research focused on the properties of crystals. His published works included studies of dislocations and imperfections in crystal structures, the effect of irradiation on crystals, and the process of diffusion in crystalline materials. In 1962 Seitz was elected president of the National Academy of Sciences in Washington, a position which he held for 6 years. In that same year, he became a trustee of the Rockefeller University and in 1968 he went on to become president of the Rockefeller University. In 1973 he received the National Medal of Science, the nation's highest award in science, for his contributions "to the foundation of the modern quantum theory of the solid state of matter."
Among his numerous honors and awards, Dr. Seitz received the Franklin Medal in 1965, the Herbert Hoover Medal in 1968, the Defense Department Distinguished Service Award in Awards in 1968, the NASA distinguished Service in 1969, the Compton Award, the highest award of the American Institute of Physics, in 1970, and the James Madison Medal of Princeton University in 1978. In 1979 he received his second NASA Distinguished Public Service Medal presented for his "dedicated service as chairman of the NASA Space Program Advisory Council from 1973 to 1977. " In addition to the Rockefeller University, 26 universities in this country and abroad have awarded him honorary degrees. In 1983 he received the Fourth Vannevar Bush Award presented by the National Science Board of the National Science Foundation and the R. Loveland Memorial Award of the American College of Physicians. From 1978 to 1983 he served as vice chairman of the Board of Trustees of the Memorial Sloan - Kettering Cancer Center.
Other memberships include the American Academy of Arts and Sciences, The Century Club, the Bohemian Club, the American Philosophical Society, the American Society for Metals, the American Institute of Mining, Metallurgy and Petroleum Engineers, the American Crystallographic Society, the Optical Society of America, the Washington Academy of Science, and a number of European scientific academies.
Arrangement note
Collection is arranged in six series: 1. Business, 1929-1979 2. Chronological Files, 1969-1978 3. Archive Center, 1971-1977 4. Campus, 1968-1978 5. General Administration, 1958-1979 6. Presonal, Biographical and Misccellaneous, 1951-1968.
Arrangement mainly alphabetical and chronological by series.
Other Finding Aids
FA141 Rockefeller University records, President, Frederick Seitz, Business, Series 1. FA815 Rockefeller University records, President, Frederick Seitz, Chronological Files, Series 2. FA816 Rockefeller University records, President, Frederick Seitz, Archive Center, Series 3. FA818 Rockefeller University records, President, Frederick Seitz, General Administration, Series 5. FA819 Rockefeller University records, President, Frederick Seitz, Personal, Biographical and Miscellaneous, Series 6.
File Plan note
Former Classification: 1 304-2
Conditions Governing Access note
Records more than 25 years old are open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Material in the Rockefeller family collections that provides the names, correspondence, or activities of living members of the Rockefeller family, and/or documents the net wealth of any Rockefeller family members, is restricted from scholarly access. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Arrangement
Campus files are arranged chronologically.
Scope and Contents
Includes but not limited to: FDR Drive projects, subway projects.
New York (N.Y.); Biology -- Research; Urban policy -- New York (State) -- New York; Physical sciences; Physics; Regional planning -- New York (N.Y.); Operations management
- Campus, 1968-1978; 4; 8 Cubic Feet 16 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes Air Rights, FDR Drive projects, 63rd Street Subway projects.
  Arrangement note
  Arranged in chronological order.
  - Jackson Laboratory, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Air Rights and highways, Technical Bulletin, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Experimental Program of Fellowships, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Papers on Zoning, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Air Rights and Highways, Technical Bulletin 1964, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - International Union for the Conservation of Nature and Natural Resources, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Air Rights - FDR Drive Background Papers, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence regarding oil burners, incinerators and compactors, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Urban Development Corporation, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Report on electrical, steam and water utilities for the New York Hospital - Cornell Medical Center, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - East River subway tunnel blasting, 1964-1971 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Pollution and environmental matters, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Relevent newspaper articles, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Air Rights Project - Architect/Client general notes, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Air Rights Project - Architect/Client meeting notes, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Neurophysiology, Report of Committee on, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Air Rights - FDR Drive and East River Drive Medical Complex, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Inventory of selected community medical programs and activities of The New York Hospital - Cornell Medical Center, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Air Rights - CES Working File - East River Drive Air Rights proposal, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Air Rights - FDR Drive "Active File I" through, 1971 January (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - East River Drive Air Rights Proposal of the York Ave. Institutions, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Air Rights - FDR Drive "Active File II" through, 1971 February (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Air Rights - FDR Drive N. Y. Times article, 1971 February 17 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Air Rights - FDR Drive "Active File III" through, 1971 April (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Air Rights - FDR Drive "Active File IV" through, 1971 June (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Air Rights - FDR Drive - Dr. Sunderlin: East Side Association meeting, 1971 June 2 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Air Rights - FDR Drive - Dr. Sunderlin: Air Rights staff meeting (at 3:00 pm), 1971 June 23 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Air Rights - FDR Drive "Active File V" through, 1971 August (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Air Rights - FDR Drive "Active file VI" through, 1971 October (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Caspary Auditorium construction and renovation, 1968-1974 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Syska and Hennessy, Inc., 1968-1972 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - City Planning Commission, 1969-1972 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Air Rights - FDR Drive "Active File VIII" through, 1972 May (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Air Rights - FDR Drive - N. Y. Times article, 1972 May 24 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Air Rights - FDR Drive "Active file VIII" through, 1972 March (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Air Rights Project "Black Books", 1972 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Air Rights Project, 1972 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Air Rights - FDR Drive - Working file: Interinstitutional Agreement, 1972 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Air Rights - FDR Drive "Active File X" through, 1972 August; 1 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Air Rights - FDR Drive "Active File X" through, 1972 August; 2 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Air Rights - CES Working File, Dr. Sunderlin, 1972 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Air Rights - FDR Drive "Active file XI" through, 1972 December; 1 of 4 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Air Rights - FDR Drive "Active file XI" through, 1972 December; 2 of 4 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Air Rights - FDR Drive "Active file XI" through, 1972 December; 3 of 4 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Air Rights - FDR Drive "Active file XI" through, 1972 December; 4 of 4 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Air Rights - CES Working file, 1972 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - CES Working File, Memos, 1972 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Air Rights - CES Working File - FS, DR, Rick S., SA, W-C, 1972-1973 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Air Rights - CES Working File - Sutton Terrace letter on declaration, 1972-1973 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Air Rights - CES Working File - Goodman/Berle, 1971-1973 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Air Rights - FDR Drive - Invoices, 1971-1974 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Air Rights - FDR Drive "Active File XII", 1973; 1 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Air Rights - FDR Drive "Active File XII", 1973-1975 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Air Rights - FDR Drive "Active File XIII", 1973; 1 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Air Rights - FDR Drive "Active File XIII", 1973; 2 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Air Rights Project of the York Ave. Institutions, 1973 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Environmental Sciences Review Committee (ad hoc), 1973 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Matters of Continuing Importance, 1973 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Air Rights - FDR Drive "Active Files XIV", 1973 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Air Rights Project - Selected notes of meetings, 1973 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - University Fellows Program, 1973-1974 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Air Rights - FDR Drive "Active File XII" through, 1974 December; 1 of 2 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Air Rights - FDR Drive "Active File XII" through, 1974 December; 2 of 2 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - RU Council, 1974-1975 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Planning - Physical Chemistry, 1975 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - York Avenue Mall Proposal, 1974-1976 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - FAH - Traffic Problem, 1975-1976 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - RU Council, 1975-1977 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Jenny Engineering, 1976 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Jenny Engineering, 1976-1977 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Subway - WOHL, 1976-1977 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Community Board #8, 1976-1977 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Subway - Public Hearings, 1977 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Scenario, 1977 May 31 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Mayor's Advisory Committee-63rd Street Subway, 1977 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Subway - DR letter to Academic Council, 1977 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - 63rd Street Subway, 1977 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - 63rd Street Subway, 1977 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Subway - Animal House Study, 1977 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Matters of Continuing Importance II, 1973-1977; 2 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Storch Engineering-63rd St, 1976-1978 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Subway, 1977-1978 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Sutton Terrace Rent Rolls, 1969 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Sutton Terrace Rent Rolls, 1970 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Sutton Terrace Rent Rolls, 1971 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Sutton Terrace Rent Rolls, 1972 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Sutton Terrace Rent Rolls, 1973 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Sutton Terrace Rent Rolls, 1974 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Sutton Terrace Rent Rolls, 1975 (Box 16, Folder 7)